Guide to the Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Michael McCarthy records, 1970-1998.
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Michael McCarthy records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Michael McCarthy records, 1970-1998.
6306
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill LLD, Architects
84 cubic ft.
Correspondence, preliminary design work drawings, slides, photographs, blueprints, a model, publicity and promotional materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, preliminary design work drawings, slides, photographs, blueprints, a model, publicity and promotional materials relating to Michael McCarthy's partnership in the New York office of the firm.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Michael A. McCarthy’s career as an architect spanned more than four decades and produced a wide variety of buildings for corporate and institutional clients. He also worked on interior design projects as well as preservation and rehabilitation projects for buildings belonging to, both, recent and historic past. McCarthy also served on art advisory committees, most notably that of the Chase Manhattan Bank.
Michael Anthony McCarthy was born on July 15, 1934 in Buffalo, New York. In 1957, he received the Bachelor of Architecture degree at Cornell University, where his fifth-year thesis project won accolades. In 1957, he worked briefly for the firm Harbach and Clark. Upon graduation he was commissioned as a Second Lieutenant in the Army and chose to do active duty in the Far East, where he visited places such as Korea, Japan, Hong Kong, Hawaii, and Macau. After completing his army service, he was granted the Eidlitz Fellowship, an award administered by the Department of Architecture at Cornell. He then worked for three years for Foit and Baschnagel, until 1963, when he received the license to practice architecture in New York State, and became a member of the American Institute of Architects. He received his M.Arch. degree in 1964 from Graduate School of Design at Harvard University.
In the autumn of 1964, McCarthy was hired by Skidmore, Owings & Merrill (SOM), a leading architectural firm credited with iconic modernist works. McCarthy’s work as a Junior Designer for the Gordon Bunshaft designed headquarters of the American Can Company in Greenwich, Connecticut led to his promotion to Participating Associate in 1967, and to Partner in 1973. Worldwide, McCarthy has designed mixed-use, office, residential, and recreational complexes for sites in Europe, the Far East, the Middle East, and Latin America. His awareness of and sensitivity to cultures outside the United States were particularly notable in the Middle East, where he designed interiors for the Joint Banking Center, the Commercial Bank of Kuwait, the Al Ahli Bank in Kuwait, and the National Commercial Bank of Saudi Arabia in New York, among others. His work for the Chase Manhattan Bank, which he considers as among the most rewarding and satisfying experiences of his career, consisted of designs for new buildings as well as significant contributions to the style and experience of their interiors, both through his own designs and by serving on their art committee. Over the course of his career, he also contributed to the interior designs of corporate clients, such as General Electric, Texaco, IBM, and Chrysler. McCarthy’s work with SOM has won many honors and awards.
He served on the Cornell University Council and the College of Architecture’s Advisory Council endowed a Chair of Architectural Theory at the Cornell University College of Architecture, Art, and Planning; and gifted to the Cornell University Library of the drawings, slides, photographs, and other related materials documenting his career as an architect He regarded the gift of his papers to Cornell as one of the most important contributions he has made to architectural education. He also provided a research fund for use of the collection by students and scholars.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, preliminary design work drawings, slides, photographs, blueprints, a model, publicity and promotional materials relating to Michael McCarthy's partnership in the New York office of the firm. Major projects include: the Islamic Cultural Center, New York; Megaworld Place and Petron Megaplaza in Manila; Pratt Institute Master Plan and Residential Center; Transitional Housing for the Homeless, New York; Commercial Bank of Kuwait; Beijing Mixed Use Developments, Banque Bruxelles; General Electric Corporate Headquarters, Fairfield Connecticut; and the Greenville-Spartanburg Airport.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill LLD, Architects.; McCarthy, Michael A.
Subjects:
Architecture--Details; Architectural design.; Architectural firms.; Architects.
Form and Genre Terms:
Blueprints.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Complete finding aid available on-line at: http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/6306McCarthySOM/
Project list of plans and drawings is filed in the accession folder.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Early Years, 1934-1951
Boxes 27, 31, 37-38
Series II. Architectural Education, 1952-57 and 1963-64
Boxes 27, 31-32, 35, 37-38, 52
Cornell University, School of Architecture, 1952-1957
Harvard University, Graduate School of Design, 1963-1964
Series III. Military Service and Travel, 1957-1964
Boxes 27, 31, 52
Military Service
Eidlitz Traveling Fellowship, 1959-1960
Series IV. Early Architectural Career, 1957-1963
Boxes 27, 32, 52
Harbach and Clark, Architects
Foit and Baschnagel, Architects
Miscellaneous
Series V. Correspondence, 1952-1999
Boxes 27-28, 31
Family Correspondence, 1952-1969
Cornell University
Other Correspondence
Series VI. Architectural Career, 1964-1997
Boxes 25, 28-31, 35, 38
Material Not Concerning Specific Projects or Built Works
Daily Desk Calendar/Diaries
General Historical and Descriptive Material Concerning Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, Architects LLP
Chase Manhattan Bank Art Program
Texaco Art Program
Honors and Awards
Miscellaneous SOM (Non-project) Correspondence and Other Materials
Lectures, Oral History, and Other Material
Series VII. Architectural Projects, Commissions, and Built Works, 1964-1998 (SOM Years)
Boxes 1-27, 31-34, 36, 38-51 and Map Cases
Sorted alphabetically
9 West 57th Street - 1166 Avenue of the Americas projects
Abu Dhabi National Oil Company - Cairo Ophthalmology Hospital
Chase Manhattan Bank projects
Chemical Bank - Hospital for Special Surgery projects
IBM Corporate Headquarters - Lever House
Mangaf Resort Hotel - Presbyterian Hospital of New York
Ras Abu Soma, Egypt - Staten Island Hospital projects
TampaSphere - World Centre projects
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Early Years, 1934-1951
  - Certificate of Promotion and exercises program, Kenmore (New York) Junior High School, June 27, 1949 (Box 27, Folder 31)
  - Autographed drawing of Ted Williams by McCarthy, accompanied by a signed photograph of Williams, 1951 (Box 27, Folder 31)
  - Graduation announcement, calling card, commencement and baccalaureate programs, McCarthy's valedictory address and diploma, Clarence (New York) Central School, June 23, 1952 (Box 27, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Clarence High School and New York State Scholarship material, including photographs, awards, certificates, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 32)
  - Remembrance of Confirmation, Church of St. Paul, Kenmore, New York, Clarence Central School graduation photograph, November 10, 1946 (Box 31)
  - The Saga, yearbooks of Clarence Central School, 1951 and 1952 (Box 37)
  - Bausch & Lomb Honorary Science Medal presented to McCarthy "in recognition of superior scientific scholarship", June 23, 1952 (Box 38)
- Series II. Architectural Education, 1952-57 and 1963-64
  - Cornell University, School of Architecture, 1952-1957
    - Cornell University Official Publication, College of Architecture Announcement, January 27, 1952 (Box 27, Folder 33)
    - Certificate of membership, Gargoyle Society (architectural honorary society) Diploma, Cornell University, Bachelor of Architecture, 1957 (Box 31)
    - Portfolio documenting McCarthy's student years at Cornell's College of Architecture, including work done in design studio, drawing and painting classes, and extracurricular activities, 1952-1957 (Box 32)
    - Design for a Thesis, An Institute of Oriental Studies in Borg el Arab, Egypt, 1957 (Box 32)
      The project was given a First Medal under the Beaux Arts system of grading and was awarded the Charles Goodwin Sands Memorial medal given by the College of Architecture for best thesis design.
    - Photographs, unmounted, additional to the portfolio, of McCarthy's student work at Cornell The Cornell Engineer 22, February 1957 (Box 32)
    - Commencement and Senior Week announcement, invitations, and commencement program, June 10, 1957 (Box 37)
    - ROTC Summer Camp yearbook and certificate, Fort Lee, Virginia, 1955 (Box 37)
    - Kappa Delta Rho Fraternity "Ordo Honorium" certificate, Undated (Box 37)
    - Kappa Delta Rho Fraternity "Ordo Honorium" medal Jewelry and other memorabilia with the insignia of Kappa Delta Rho, Gargoyle Society, and Tau Beta Pi (engineering honorary society), Undated (Box 38)
    - Slides of McCarthy's senior thesis project, "An Institute of Oriental Studies for the Dominican Order, Borg al-Arab, Egypt", 1957 (Box 52)
  - Harvard University, Graduate School of Design, 1963-1964
    - Application to the Graduate School of Design of Harvard University and to the School of Art and Architecture of Yale University of the academic year (1963-1964), captions, 1963-1964 (Box 32)
    - Application portfolio, Undated (Box 35)
    - Diploma, Harvard University, Master of Architecture, 1964 (Box 31)
    - Entrance tickets and program, Harvard University Commencement, June 11, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 34)
- Series III. Military Service and Travel, 1957-1964
  - Military Service
    - Commission, Second Lieutenant, United States Army, June 10, 1957 (Box 31)
    - Honorable discharge, April 23, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 35)
    - Newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 35)
  - Eidlitz Traveling Fellowship, 1959-1960
    - Report of trip to Thomas Mackesey, Dean, Cornell University, School of Architecture, Undated (Box 27, Folder 35)
    - Annotated list of slides made on the trip, Undated (Box 27, Folder 35)
    - Slides, Undated (Box 52)
- Series IV. Early Architectural Career, 1957-64
  - A. Harbach abd Clark, Architects, Buffalo, New York, 1957
    - Mr. and Mrs. Levant M. Himelein, Jr., Residence Gowanda, New York - Portfolio, 1957 (Box 32)
  - B. Foit and Baschnagel, Architects, Buffalo, New York, 1960–1963
    McCarthy was involved in the design of some of the projects below; in others, he executed working drawings for the firm.
    - Miscellaneous materials documenting Projects, above Newspaper articles, some undated; others from the Buffalo Evening News, April 25, 1963 (Box 32)
    - Harlem Road Branch Library (image) Cheektowaga, New York, 1962 (Box 32)
    - Anderson-Lee Library Sliver Creek, New York, 1963 (Box 32)
    - Slides, Undated (Box 52)
    - Cost estimates, Undated (Box 32)
  - C. Miscellaneous
    - Curriculum vitae and photographs, c. 1964 (Box 27, Folder 36)
    - Portfolio used in applying for positions with architectural firms in New York., Undated (Box 32)
      Includes work done at Cornell, at Harvard, and while employed with Harbach and Clark
    - Page from Fortune showing a view of McCarthy’s apartment in Columbia Heights, Brooklyn, February 1970 (Box 32)
- Series V. Correspondence, 1952-1999
  - A. Family Correspondence, 1952–1969
    Michael McCarthy to his parents, Mr. and Mrs. Joseph W. McCarthy)
    - Freshman year at Cornell, September 1952–May 1953 (Box 27, Folder 37)
    - Sophomore and junior years at Cornell; ROTC summer camp, September 1953–August 1955 (Box 27, Folder 38)
    - Senior and fifth years at Cornell, September 1955–May 1957 (Box 27, Folder 39)
    - Military service; Eidlitz travel, November 1957–February 1960 (Box 27, Folder 40)
    - Harvard and early career at SOM, September 1963–December 1965 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, January 1966–December 1967 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, January 1968–December 1969 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - B. Cornell University
    - Cornell University Council, Undated (Box 28, Folder 4-6)
    - Kappa Delta Rho Fraternity, Michael A. McCarthy Architectural Scholarship, Undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Cornell College of Architecture, Art and Planning Advisory Council, Undated (Box 28, Folder 8-9)
    - Cornell College of Architecture, Art and Planning, Michael A. McCarthy Professorship in Architectural Theory, Undated (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Cornell College of Architecture, Art, and Planning 125th anniversary events, Undated (Box 28, Folder 11-12)
    - Cornell University Library, Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Michael A. McCarthy and Skidmore, Owings & Merrill LLP, Papers (reasons for and importance of collection), Undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Cornell University correspondence, Undated (Box 28, Folder 14-15)
    - Cornell Campaign bookplate, framed, to honor McCarthy’s contributions, 1990–1995 (Box 31)
  - C. Other Correspondence
    - childreach, U.S. Member of Plan International, McCarthy’s sponsorship of his foster child, Adrian Navarrete, and his family, in Guayaquil, Ecuador, 1986–1996 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Cornell Catholic Community, Undated (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - United Way of New York City, Architects and Engineers Division, Michael A. McCarthy, Chair of the 1988–1989 campaign, 1988-1989 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Indian Correspondence, 1997 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1999-2002 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - McCarthy’s personal art collection, Undated (Box 28, Folder 18)
- Series VI. Architectural Career, 1964-1997
  Material other than that concerning specific projects or built works
  Note: These materials were collected and given by Michael A. McCarthy with the intention of documenting for students and scholars "the practice of architecture in a large multidisciplinary firm."
  - A. Daily Desk Calendar/Diaries, 1969-1997
    - Daily desk calendars/diaries, 1969–1997 (Box 30)
  - B. General Historical and Descriptive Material Concerning Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, Architects LLP
    - SOM Firmwide Operating report, April 25, 1997 (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Brochure System sample pages, Undated (Box 35)
    - Bound SOM brochure: Design Responsive to Islamic Culture, Undated (Box 35)
    - McCarthy’s curriculum vitae in Brochure System format, Undated (Box 31)
    - Skidmore, Owings & Merrill Foundation 1983 Third Annual Travelling Fellowships, 1983 (Box 31)
    - Brochure System implementation manual, Undated (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - SOM stationery samples, Undated (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Minutes of SOM partners’ meetings, Undated (Box 28, Folder 20-22)
    - Appraisals and other information regarding SOM’s art collection, Undated (Box 28, Folder 23)
    - Promotional materials for McCarthy’s work in Russia, India, and China, Undated (Box 28, Folder 24)
    - Published articles about SOM, Undated (Box 25)
    - Correspondence, resumes, portfolios, and other material relating to the publication of Architecture of Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, 1984–1994, particularly the Introduction by Joan Ockman, 1995 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Interior design department at SOM, Undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - SOM 50th anniversary invitations and programs, Undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Traveling Fellows: Fifteen Years of Student Awards (Chicago: SOM Foundation, 1997)., 1997 (Box 29, Folder 14)
      Book, CD, poster, and correspondence
    - SOM 50th anniversary brochure, Undated (Box 31)
    - SOM 50th anniversary memorabilia, Undated (Box 38)
    - “Archidek Architectural Cards for Collecting” showing various SOM buildings, Undated (Box 38)
  - C. Chase Manhattan Bank Art Program
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank Art Collection, 1980 Acquisitions, 1980 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank Art Collection, 1981 Acquisitions, 1981 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank Art Collection, 1982 Acquisitions, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank Art Collection, 1983 Acquisitions, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - The Chase Manhattan Bank Art Collection, Acquisitions for 1984, 1984 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - Chase Manhattan: The First Ten Years of Collecting, 1959–1969 (Atlanta: High Museum of Art, 1982), 1982 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - Contemporary Spanish Art: A Selection of Recent Acquisitions from the Collection of the Chase Manhattan Bank (Madrid: Banco Exterior de Espana; NY: Chase Manhattan Bank, 1984), 1984 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - Selections from the Chase Manhattan Bank Art Collection (Amherst: University Gallery, University of Massachusetts, 1981), 1981 (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    - Committee meeting agendas and minutes, published articles, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
  - D. Texaco Art Program
    - Correspondence, brochures, artists’ resumes and portfolio images, Undated (Box 29, Folder 6-7)
  - E. Honors and Awards
    General and SOM awards
    - Published articles and other materials concerning various awards to the SOM firm and/or non-McCarthy projects, Undated (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Curriculum vitae and other materials in support of McCarthy’s nomination for advancement to the College of Fellows, American Institute of Architects (FAIA), 1985 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - McCarthy’s FAIA certificate and medal; photographs, program, and other material from the New Fellows Investiture, AIA Convention, San Antonio, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - American Institute of Architects 1996 Architecture Firm Award to Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, May 1996 (Box 31)
    - The National Arts Club Medal, awarded to Skidmore, Owings & Merrill “for excellence in architecture”, November 14, 1995 (Box 38)
  - F. Miscellaneous SOM (Non-project) Correspondence and Other Materials
    - Retirement letters and miscellaneous correspondence, Undated (Box 29, Folder 10-11)
  - G. Lectures, Oral History, and Other Material
    - Lectures to various groups describing the work of SOM, Undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Beginnings in Architectural Education: Proceedings of the ACSA/EAAE Conference, Prague, 1993 (Washington, DC: ACSA Press, 1994), 1994 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Interviews with Michael McCarthy by Rebecca Davidson concerning his life and work, made at Cornell University Library, 1999-2000 (Box 30)
    - License to Practice Architecture, University of the State of New York, Education Department, May 3, 1963 (Box 31)
    - American Institute of Architects, Certificate of Membership, July 1, 1963 (Box 31)
    - National Council of Architectural Registration Boards (NCARB) Certificate, November 15, 1974 (Box 31)
    - “Michael A. McCarthy Archives Project: The Documentation of an Architect’s Career”, Undated (Box 31)
      Brochure
    - Architectural Career (project list), 1969-1997 (Box 56, Folder 6)
- Series VII. Architectural Projects, Commissions, and Built Works, 1964-1998 (SOM Years)
  - 9 West 57th Street - 1166 Avenue of the Americas projects
    - 9 West 57th Street (Solow Building), New York, 1973
      Gordon Bunshaft, design partner
      1981 - 1983; 1994 - 1997 Renovations
      9 West 57th is a 49-story travertine and glass tower with a unique sloping base. Renovations were first made to Sheldon Solow's suite in 1981 - 1983. In 1994 - 1997, renovations were also made to Mr. Solow's suite and garage.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 39)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 47)
      - Project description, specifications, project personnel roster, meeting minutes, correspondence, and newspaper clippings., Undated (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - 61 Broadway (Winthrop Financial Corporation / First Winthrop), New York, 1984 - 1987
      Renovation of a lobby and first four floors of the facade of a building originally designed by Francis Kimball in 1914. Changes also included a new limestone facade and entrance loggie more in keeping with the building's original Beaux Arts character. Winner of the 1988 Tucker Award
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 39)
      - Project summary, location map, awards application, materials catalog, newspaper clippings, and published articles, Undated (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - 85 Broad Street, New York, 1980
      Roy O. Allen, design partner
      Renovations, Goldman, Sachs Trading Room, 1992 - 1994
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 39)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 47)
      - Project summary, Undated (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - 570 Lexington Avenue (General Electric Building), New York, 1983 - 1988
      The restoration of the facade of this historic 1920s-era Art Deco building included replacement or preservation of fenestration, cleaning and replacement of brickwork in an array of special shapes and colors, and terra-cotta details in accordance with guidelines established by the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission in 1987. The project also included interior renovations and a dramatic lighting of the tower top, giving the General Electric Building a distinctive outline on the Manhattan skyline.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 39)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 47)
      - Project summary, list of subcontractors, published articles, and awards applications, Undated (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - American Institute of Architects New York Chapter 1993 Design Award for Preservation; New York State Association of Architects Citation for Design (1993), 1993 (Box 34)
      - Publicity brochure for Wolfgang Hoyt Photography featuring the General Electric Building, Undated (Box 34)
    - 757 Third Avenue (Winthrop Financial Corporation / First Winthrop), New York, 1984 - 1986
      Redesign of the lobby of a 1961 building by Emery Roth & Sons. The new design features rich decorative marbles and a hemispherical dome with indirect lighting. Also included in the project were tenant floor modifications of the 33-story office building
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 39)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 47)
      - Project summary, awards application, and newspaper clippings., Undated (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - 919 Third Avenue, New York, 1966
      Roger Radford, senior designer
      Michael A. McCarthy, junior designer
      1986 - 1990 Renovations
      Renovations of this building, originally designed by SOM in 1966, included the plaza, lobby, and elevator cabs.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 39)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 47)
      - Project summary and newspaper clippings., Undated (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - 1166 Avenue of the Americas, New York, 1969 - 1971
      - Newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Abu Dhabi National Oil Company - Cairo Ophthalmology Hospital
    - Abu Dhabi National Oil Company (ADNOC) Exhibition Center (Petroleum Exhibition Hall), Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates, 1996-1997
      A conference and exhibition center with a cafeteria, gift shop, display area, and library.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 39)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 47)
      - Conceptual design proposal, copies of photographs of model, Undated (Box 25, Folder 14)
      - Prospectus with reduced copies of drawings and cost estimates, Undated (Box 34)
    - Abu Dhabi National Oil Company (ADNOC) Headquarters, Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirate, 1996
      Multi-story office tower that also includes a prayer room, training center, auditorium, and landscaped area with a pool.
      - Design drawings (Box 15)
      - Presentation drawings - Elevations, Section, Undated (Box 72)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 47)
      - Reduced copies of drawings, maps, and promotional literature on the United Arab Emirates, Undated (Box 25, Folder 14)
      - Building Model (approximately 25" x 36" x 44"), Undated (Map-case Item)